Guide to the Allegheny County, Pa. Health Department, Bureau of Air Pollution Control Records, 1941-1978 AIS.1980.07
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Allegheny County, Pa. Health Department, Bureau of Air Pollution Control Records
1941-1978
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Allegheny County (Pa.). Bureau of Air Pollution Control
AIS.1980.07
1.68 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
The Allegheny County Bureau of Air Pollution Control Records contains materials related to smoke control and air pollution. It includes minutes of the County Smoke Control Advisory Committee; annual reports and ordinances for Pittsburgh and Allegheny County; research, studies and informational reports from Pittsburgh Bureau of Smoke Prevention, County Bureau of Air Pollution Control, the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, and other organizations on pollution concerns.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Howard Weisz on April 28, 1980.
History
In 1941 Pittsburgh instituted its first smoke control ordinance and established the Bureau of Smoke Prevention, under the city's Department of Health, in order to collect data and administer the new law. In 1949, Allegheny County passed its first smoke control ordinance and simultaneously established its own smoke control agency, the Bureau of Air Pollution Control (alternately called the Bureau of Smoke Control). Both the city and the county continued to act separately until the county took full responsibility in 1957.
In 1947, the Board of County Commissioners appointed a Smoke Abatement Advisory Committee of seventeen citizens under the chairmanship of Dr. Edward R. Weidlein, Director of the Mellon Institute of Industrial Research. This committee was charged with the duty of drawing up an ordinance which would be applicable to the conditions existing in the County. After the enactment of this ordinance in 1949, the Bureau of Air Pollution was formed under the jurisdiction of the County Health Department. In addition, a permanent advisory committee was established and renamed the Smoke Control Advisory Committee. The advisory committee, composed of scientists, economists, and industry leaders, has played an important role in smoke control in Pittsburgh.
Over the years, the Allegheny County Bureau of Air Pollution Control has become increasingly sophisticated in its collection of data and research methods. Additional, more stringent ordinances have been passed and licensing and fee collection systems have been put into practice. Thirty-four research reports, prepared by the Bureau's directors and staff members, are included in this collection.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Scope and Content Notes
The Bureau of Air Pollution Control Records span the years 1941-1978. Minutes and organizational charts trace the bureaucratic history (1947-1954) of Allegheny County's Smoke Control Advisory Committee. There are annual reports from the Advisory Steel Research Subcommittee of County Bureau of Air Pollution Control (1960-1969) as well as annual reports covering smoke control for the city and county (1941-1969). Also collected are various city and county ordinance, rules, and regulations dealing with air pollution (1946-1978). Finally, there are several reports done by the county's Bureau of Air Pollution Control, the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, and by external researchers on subjects related to air pollution control.
Previous Citation
Allegheny County, Pa. Health Department. Bureau of Air Pollution Control Records, 1941-1978, AIS.1980.04, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Accruals
An addition of five folders was accrued in 1984. The material dates from 1949-1965 and is located at the end of Box 4. The files include correspondence; personnel rosters; reports; salary information; and speeches.
Related Material
Allegheny County Air Pollution Advisory Committee Records, 1959-1986, AIS.1992.03, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Smoke prevention -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Air -- Pollution -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Business and Industry; Environment; Speeches; Health and medicine; Correspondence; Reports; Minutes (Administrative records); Pittsburgh (Pa.); Allegheny County (Pa.); Government; Smoke prevention -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; United States. Environmental Protection Agency; Pittsburgh (Pa.). Bureau of Smoke Prevention; Allegheny County (Pa.). Health Department; Allegheny County (Pa.). Smoke Control Advisory Committee; Allegheny County (Pa.). Bureau of Air Pollution Control; Wurts, Thomas C.; Schreibeis, Lee
- Minutes - Allegheny County Smoke Control Advisory Committee, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Minutes - Allegheny County Smoke Control Advisory Committee, 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Organizational charts for Bureau of Smoke Control, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous correspondence, 1948 and April - December, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Annual Reports for Bureau of Smoke Prevention, 1941-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Annual Reports for Bureau of Air Pollution Control, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Annual Reports for Bureau of Air Pollution Control, 1952-1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Annual Reports for Bureau of Air Pollution Control, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Annual Reports for Bureau of Air Pollution Control, Advisory Steel Research Subcommittee, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Annual Reports for Bureau of Air Pollution Control, Advisory Steel Research Subcommittee, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Ordinances for City of Pittsburgh, Department of Public Health, 1946-1954 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Ordinances for Allegheny County Health Department, Bureau of Air Pollution Control, 1949, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Rules and regulations, Allegheny County Health Department, 1949-1978 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- In-house reports, 1941-1969 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- In-house reports, 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- In-house reports, 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- External reports, 1962-1977 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Informational reports, 1952-1962 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Informational reports, 1967-1973 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Environmental Protection Agency reports, 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Environmental Protection Agency reports, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Table of organization - personnel rosters (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Letters, August 11, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Monthly activity reports, March - October, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Speeches, etc. by Lee Schreibeis, Jr., 1959 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Speeches, etc. by Thomas C. Wurts, 1949-1958 (Box 4, Folder 5)